Chapter 86.
The tail.
Other poets have warbbled the praises of the soft eye of the antelope and the
lovely plumage of the bird that never ellightes. less celestial, I celebrate a tail.
Reckoning the largestsized sperm whale's tail to begin at that point of the
trunk, where it tapers to about the girth of a man, it comprises upon its
upper surface alone an area of at least 50 square ft. The compact round body of
its root expands into two broad firm flat palms or flukes gradually sholing
away to less than an inch in thickness.
At the crotch or junction these flukes slightly overlap, then sideways recede
from each other like wings, leaving a wide vacancy between. In no living thing
are the lines of beauty more exquisitly defined than in the crescentic borders
of these flukes. At its utmost expansion in the fullgrown whale, the tail will
considerably exceed 20 feet across.
The entire member seems a dense webbed bed of welded senus, but cut into it and
you find that three distinct strata compose it, upper, middle, and lower.
The fibers in the upper and lower layers are long and horizontal. Those of the
middle one very short and running crosswise between the outside layers.
This triune structure, as much as anything else, imparts power to the
tale, to the student of old Roman walls.
The middle layer will furnish a curious parallel to the thin course of tiles,
always alternating with the stone in those wonderful relics of the antique,
and which undoubtedly contribute so much to the great strength of the masonry.
But as if this vast local power in the tendonous tail were not enough, the
whole bulk of the Leviathan is knit over with a warp and woof of muscular fibers
and filaments which passing on either side the loins and running down into the
flukes insensibly blend with them and largely contribute to their might, so
that in the tail the confluent measurless force of the whole whale
seems concentrated to a point. Could annihilation occur to matter if this
were the thing to do it.
Nor does this, its amazing strength, at all tend to the graceful flexion
of its motions, where infantileness of ease undulates through a titanism of
power. On the contrary, those motions derive their most appalling beauty from
it. Real strength never impairs beauty or harmony, but it often bestows it. And
in everything imposingly beautiful, strength has much to do with the magic.
Take away the tide tendons that all over seem bursting from the marble in carved
Hercules, and its charm would be gone.
As the devout Echerman lifted the linen sheet from the naked corpse of Gerta, he
was overwhelmed with the massive chest of the man that seemed as a Roman
triumphal arch. When Angelo paints even God the Father in human form, mark what
robustness is there. And whatever they may reveal of the divine love in the
sun, the soft, curled, hermaphroditical Italian pictures in which his idea has
been most successfully embodied. These pictures, so destitute as they are of
all brrawniness, hint nothing of any power, but the mere negative feminine
one of submission and endurance, which on all hands, it is conceited, form the
peculiar practical virtues of his teachings.
Such as the subtle elasticity of the organ I treat of that whether wielded in
sport or in earnest or in anger, whatever be the mood it be in, its
flexions are invariably marked by exceeding grace. Therein no fair's arm
can transcend it. Five great motions are peculiar to it. First, when used as a
fin for progression, second when used as a mace in battle. Third, in sweeping.
Fourth in lob tailing, fifth in peaking flukes.
First being horizontal in its position, the Leviathan's tail acts in a different
manner from the tails of all other sea creatures. It never wriggles in man or
fish. Wriggling is a sign of inferiority. To the whale, his tail is
the sole means of propulsion.
scroll-wise coiled forwards beneath the body and then rapidly sprung backwards.
It is this which gives that singular darting, leaping motion to the monster
when furiously swimming, his side fins only serve to steer by.
Second, it is a little significant that while one sperm whale only fights
another sperm whale with his head and jaw, nevertheless, in his conflicts with
man, he chiefly and contemptuously uses his tail. In striking at a boat, he
swiftly curves away his flukes from it, and the blow is only inflicted by the
recoil. If it be made in the unobstructed air, especially if it
descend to its mark, the stroke is then simply irresistible. No ribs of man or
boat can withstand it. Your only salvation lies in eluding it. But if it
comes sideways through the opposing water, then partly owing to the light
buoyancy of the whaleboat and the elasticity of its materials, a cracked
rib or a dashed plank or two, a sort of stitch in the side is generally the most
serious result. These submerged side blows are so often received in the
fishery that they are accounted mere child's play. Someone strips off a frock
and the hole is stopped.
Third, I cannot demonstrate it, but it seems to me that in the whale the sense
of touch is concentrated in the tail, for in this respect there is a delicacy
in it only equaled by the daintiness of the elephant's trunk. This delicacy is
chiefly evinced in the action of sweeping, when, in maidenly gentleness
the whale, with a certain soft slowness moves his immense flukes from side to
side upon the surface of the sea. And if he feels but a sailor's whisker, woe to
that sailor, whiskers and all, what tenderness there is in that preliminary
touch. Had this tale any prehensile power, I should straightway bethink me
of Dharmmanad's elephant that so frequented the flower market, and with
low salutations presented nose gaze to damsels, and then caressed their zones.
On more accounts than one, a pity it is that the whale does not possess this
prehensel virtue in his tail. For I have heard of yet another elephant that when
wounded in the fight, curved round his trunk and extracted the dart.
Fourth, stealing unawares upon the whale in the fancied security of the middle of
solitary seas, you find him unbent from the vast corpulence of his dignity, and
kitten-like. He plays on the ocean as if it were a hearth, but still you see his
power in his play. The broad palms of his tail are flirted high into the air,
then smiting the surface, the thunderous concussion resounds for miles. You would
almost think a great gun had been discharged, and if you notice the light
wreath of vapor from the spiracle at his other extremity, you would think that
that was the smoke from the touch hole.
Fifth, as in the ordinary floating posture of the Leviathan, the flukes lie
considerably below the level of his back, they are then completely out of
sight beneath the surface. But when he is about to plunge into the deeps, his
entire flukes with at least 30 ft of his body are tossed erect in the air, and so
remain vibrating a moment till they downward shoot out of view. Accepting
the sublime breach somewhere else to be described, this peaking of the whale's
flukes is perhaps the grandest sight to be seen in all animated nature. Out of
the bottomless profoundities the gigantic tail seems spasmotically
snatching at the highest heaven. So in dreams have I seen majestic Satan
thrusting forth his tormented colossal claw from the flame Baltic of hell. But
in gazing at such scenes, it is all in all what mood you are in. If in the
Dantean the devils will occur to you, if in that of Isaiah the archangels,
standing at the mast head of my ship during a sunrise that crimson sky and
sea, I once saw a large herd of whales in the east, all heading towards the
sun, and for a moment vibrating in concert with peaked flukes, as it seemed
to me at the time, such a grand embodiment of adoration of the gods was
never beheld, even in Persia. the home of the fire worshippers. As Tammy
Filipotter testified of the African elephant, I then testified of the whale,
pronouncing him the most devout of all beings. For according to King Juba, the
military elephants of antiquity often hailed the morning with their trunks
uplifted in the profoundest silence.
The chance comparison in this chapter between the whale and the elephant, so
far as some aspects of the tail of the one and the trunk of the other are
concerned, should not tend to place those two opposite organs on an
equality, much less the creatures to which they respectively belong. For as
the mightiest elephant is but a terrier to Leviathan, so compared with
Leviathan's tail, his trunk is but the stock of a lily. The most direful blow
from the elephant's trunk were as the playful tap of a fan, compared with the
measurless crush and crash of the sperm whales ponderous flukes, which in
repeated instances have one after the other, hurled entire boats with all
their oars and crews into the air, very much as an Indian juggler tosses his balls.
Footnote. Though all comparison in the way of general bulk between the whale
and the elephant is preposterous, in as much as in that particular the elephant
stands in much the same respect to the whale as the dog does to the elephant.
Nevertheless, there are not wanting some points of curious similitude. Among
these is the spout. It is well known that the elephant will often draw up
water or dust in his trunk and then, elevating it, jet it forth in a stream.
End of footnote.
The more I consider this mighty tale, the more do I deplore my inability to
express it. At times there are gestures in it, which, though they would well
grace the hand of man, remain wholly inexplicable. In an extensive herd, so
remarkable occasionally are these mystic gestures, that I have heard hunters, who
have declared them akin to Freemason signs and symbols, that the whale,
indeed, by these methods intelligently conversed with the world. Nor are there
wanting other motions of the whale in his general body, full of strangeness,
and unaccountable to his most experienced asalent. Dissect him how I
may, then I go but skin deep, I know him
not, and never will. But if I know not even the tail of this whale, how
understand his head? Much more how comprehend his face, when face he has
none. Thou shalt see my back parts, my tail, he seems to say, but my face shall
not be seen. But I cannot completely make out his back parts and hint what he
will about his face. I say again, he has no face.